Okay, בוקר טוב *boker tov*. גוט ערב שבת Shabbos, *Good erev Shabbat*.
Today's דף *daf* is דף ז *daf zayin*. We pick up at
the two dots about eight lines down. Let me quickly review because
yesterday's דף *daf* we saw a ברייתא braisa, *braita*, really a quote
of a תוספתא *Tosefta*, slightly different version in ours, which listed the
four רשויות *reshuyot* for שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, and this will last us
for another two דפים *dapim* or day and a half to get
us till the next משנה Mishna. *mishna*. And it listed that there
are four רשויות *reshuyot*. רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid. *Reshut hayachid*, which we
saw was defined as a space four by four טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*
with walls ten טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* high, even if the walls are
below it, like on a post or on a or in a
ditch or something of that nature. We mentioned that there was a
debate of the ראשונים *Rishonim* whether it's three walls or four walls.
And then we had a רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim, *Reshut harabim* which
it said was a major public square or a major road, although
it did not exactly tell you how major the road had to
be. We mentioned that there was another criteria elsewhere of sixteen אמות
Amos *amot*, about twenty-four feet, and then becomes the real question how
else do you define it, where some go so far as to
say you need 600,000 people that it's available to using it daily
and so on, or major road between cities, straight, other types of
criteria that get thrown in, and which is a very critical question
because the other thing we saw was a debate of the חכמים
Chachamim *Chachamim* and רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* if you can have
walls around a רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim. *Reshut harabim* or do we
say אתי רבים rabbim ומבטלי מחיצתא *Ati rabim umvatli mechitza*. The רבים
rabim. *rabim* come and they negate the meaning of the walls. And
if we say that, which we basically do, it means you cannot
have an עירוב Eiruv, *eruv*, what we call an עירוב *eruv*, when
there is a real biblical רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim *Reshut harabim*. So
it's very critical what we define as the criteria, if we say
that right now mostly we're dealing with כרמלית Carmelis. *carmelit* and not
רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim, *Reshut harabim*, a, it lowers everything to a
level of a דרבנן *d'rabbanan* and b, it allows for an עירוב
*eruv*, very critical practical question. So now we can and now we've
and we've said one other interesting issue that even if a place
is surrounded by walls, if it's larger than a certain size, around
5,600 square feet, בית סאתיים *Beit Satayim*, and it's not used for
habitation, which is a very, you know, broad or abstract term what
that means, then rabbinically you cannot carry in it as well. Okay,
so now we move on to the third of the רשויות *reshuyot*,
the rabbinic רשות reshut, *reshut* which is the כרמלית Carmelis. *carmelit*. Eight
lines down, two dots on ז עמוד א Amud Aleph, *zayin amud
aleph*. Let's take a look. והכרמלית *Ve'hakarmelit*, and the כרמלית Carmelis *carmelit*.
Now אטו כולהו נמי לאו כרמלית Carmelis נינהו *Atu kulu nami lav
carmelit ninhu*? So it said, it gave a list of various things
that fell in this
כרמלית Carmelis. *carmelit* category, an ocean, a valley, thank you, other types
of things and כרמלית Carmelis. *carmelis*, which רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says means
in its more narrow sense a forest. But כרמלית Carmelis. *carmelis* also
has become not the name of a specific thing but also of
the class, of the genre. So which leads to the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s question, which is, why are you saying כרמלית karmelis, *carmelit* if
these are all in the class of כרמלית karmelis, *carmelit*, understanding כרמלית
karmelis. *carmelit* in its more later what seems to be a later
development of its abstract meaning, its meaning as a class, not the
specific example of a forest. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says כי
אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi
Yochanan, *Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan*, Rav דימי *Dimi* came,
he said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*,
לא נצרכה אלא לקרן זוית הסמוכה לרשות הרבים lo nitzrecha ela le-keren
zavis hasmucha le-reshus harabbim, *Lo nitzrecha ela le'keren zavit hasmucha lereshut harabim*.
What we're dealing with is to tell you that there's even another
case that's a כרמלית karmelis, *carmelit* that you might not have thought
was a כרמלית karmelis, *carmelit*, which is like some type of a
corner or an intruding corner into the רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim *Reshut
harabim*. דאע״ג דדחקי ביה רבים rabim, ועיילי לגביה *De'avda gav dei de'dachki
bei rabim ve'ayli legavei*, although sometimes because the roads are like overfilled
and the רבים rabim, *rabim* push forward and like enter into that
corner, כיון
דלא ניחא תשמישתיה nicha tashmishtei *Keivan delo nicha tashmishtei*, since it's not
used in a convenient way, ככרמלית דמי *Ke'carmelis dami*, it's like a
כרמלית karmelis. *carmelis*. So right, so we there's a whole class of
things which are, you know, which are
quasi connected to רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim *Reshut harabim* and the key
question is, are they enough part of רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim *Reshut
harabim* to get that status of רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim. *Reshut harabim*
or not? So, you know, we have some things that maybe are
closer to the idea of a רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid *Reshut hayachid*
like a front yard,
although we get mentioned that the חצר *chatzer* in the time of
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was effectively surrounded by wall of the walls
of the surrounding houses. But a lot of the cases of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* are things which are sort of, you know, associated
with רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim *Reshut harabim*, צידי דרשות הרבים *Tzidei de'Reshut
harabim*, the shoulders of רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim. *Reshut harabim*. You know,
we had the סטו *stav*, or איסטו *istav*, or איסטווניתא *istavinah*, which
was whatever, which was either some types of columns or places that
the merchants put their wares or people would go to but it
would not be a major thoroughfare and so on. So here is
where and the question with all of these is, are they considered
רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim *Reshut harabim* or not? So if they're independent
spaces, then you have to ask like is it a place where
is major thoroughfare, the masses gather or more commonly that they pass
through, type of a major street. But what if they're like at
the edges of the street? Well, or there's different places within the
street which we'll get to in a minute. There the key question
is going to be whether it is convenient to use or not
convenient to use. And this is an important criteria of רשות הרבים,
Reshus HaRabim, which is distinct from that of רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid,
You know, everybody initially says and we've, the question has come up
more than once here, which is, does ownership matter? And the answer
is no. You could have a רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid. that is
with walls that's owned by the masses. However, that rabbinically might require
an עירוב, but biblically it doesn't matter. You could have a רשות
הרבים, Reshus HaRabim. you know, for what some reason, I don't know,
there's a major street which I happen to own but I let
everybody use as their major thoroughfare, it's still a רשות הרבים. Reshus
HaRabim Ownership does not matter. But what does matter, not for רשות
היחיד, reshut ha-yachid. but what does matter biblically for רשות הרבים Reshus
HaRabim is use. That whereas one of the qualities that make it
a רשות הרבים, rishus harabbim. I mean again, which we're not, it's
not a physical quality is, might have to be sixteen אמות amos,
wide, but beyond that its quality is defined by how it's used.
So one of the important questions is, you know, even if space
is nearby, not just are they physically connected, how are they used?
And the way in which it's used becomes a very central feature
of רשות הרבים rishus harabbim. to distinct from רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid,
So here's the גמרא Gemara saying if you have some type of
a corner, it's not exactly clear how it's imagining this corner. I
don't know, does, does שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz offer a picture for that? No.
Okay. I don't know if Artscroll does. Anyway, רש״י Rashi has a
description which is a little hard to exactly get your head around,
but anyway, basically, the way I imagine it is, it's like a
little corner that's off of the main רשות הרבים rishus harabbim. and
that sometimes people will go into, like you know, it's a little
side street or whatever, that they'll sometimes go into if it gets
overcrowded or sometimes have to go in to get around, but nevertheless
it's not the main usage, therefore it is not considered a רשות
הרבים rishus harabbim but a כרמלית. karmelit. And that will get us
to the focus of the next discussion in the גמרא Gemara which
is how much does something have to be convenient usage to be
part of the רשות הרבים. rishus harabbim Definitely. Does he have a
picture? What picture? Let me see what picture he's got here in
the Artscroll. He does. Yeah,
that's sort of how I imagined it. Okay, yeah, right, so exactly
as I said, which is, we don't have a thing, but exactly
as I said, you've got your main street and you have some
nook here, some side street, some little niche, and that little nook
they can go into but, but it's not a convenient thing, it's
off of the main thoroughfare, it doesn't allow for easy passage and
that would be considered a כרמלית. karmelit So really anything that doesn't
qualify רשות הרבים rishus harabbim. is a כרמלית karmelit even if it's
really closely connected to the רשות הרבים. rishus harabbim. That's not always
the case in רשות הרבים rishus harabbim. though. I know, so we're
going to get to it. So everyone might have, well no, צידי
רשות הרבים Tzidei Reshus HaRabim also ruled was not a רשות הרבים,
rishus harabbim it was only רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So there's going
to be different, A, it might be debates and B, every phenomenon
might be different based on its qualities. So let's take a look
now as the גמרא Gemara, continues.
Okay. כי אתא רב דימי ki ata Rav Dimi, אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rabbi Yochanan, when Rav Dimi came and said in the name
of Rabbi Yochanan and now we're going to get another statement of
Rabbi Yochanan, what constitutes a כרמלית karmelit even though it's connected or
close to a רשות הרבים. rishus harabbim, בין העמודים נידון ככרמלית. Bein
HaAmudim nidon k’Carmelis.
Between the poles is like a, is like a כרמלית. karmelit So
basically this would sound like might be its איסטוונית, Istovanis, but of
course איסטוונית Istovanis was in the משנה. Mishna. So רש״י Rashi says
that the איסטבא Istova stoa really referred to the booths which were
like in front of the stores. And the poles were like again,
let's think of like the Cardo in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right, you had
these pillars where people would walk and that's where they would find
the stores and maybe the people with their booths, but at least
between the pillars was a place you could walk. But even though
you could walk, it's not a major thoroughfare, right? You gotta move
around the pillars, it's not so convenient, it's not direct. Like think
about, I don't know, like you know, walking under the subway tracks,
well not true, but I was thinking of a more, a more
contemporary example, like walking under, you know, the subway tracks, maybe that's
not so good example because that's a street. But anyway, but the
point is
if you're driving down Broadway and you're underneath the subway and you
want to keep going then you're underneath the subway, but if you
really want to go to the store, get parking, then you have
to come out in the space between the subway.
Right, right, so exactly. So it's some type of a thing like
that which is a type of a צידי רשות הרבים Tzidei Reshus
HaRabim in the sense that צידי רשות הרבים Tzidei Reshus HaRabim seems
to have been like a shoulder, like what happens if somebody goes
over the רשות הרבים rishus harabbim but that's not something that's used
commonly. This has a sense of a little bit more like a
sidewalk. Like it's not the main, I mean I know it's hard
for us to mix genres of cars and walking, but imagine that,
you know, where it's, where it's the space between the pillars. What?
Service road. Right, where people would go but they'd go also to
visit the stores and to whatever, but it would not be the
major part of the thoroughfare. Is that a רשות הרבים rishus harabbim
or not? So Rabbi Yochanan said no, it's a כרמלית. karmelit. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta’ama? Why? אף על גב דדרסי בה רבים, Af al
gav de’darsi bei rabim, even though the masses walk there, כיון דלא
מיסתגי להו בהדיא, keivan de’lo mistagi lehu behedya, since they don't travel
through it like directly, they have to, you know, move around the
pillars, it's not convenient, it's not direct, it's with more obstructions, ככרמלית
דמיא, k’Carmelis damya, it's like a כרמלית. karmelis הדיא Hedya is an
interesting word. הדיא Hedya can mean explicitly, but it could also mean
like directly, immediately, without you know, without sort of without any fooling
around. So whether it means sort of without circumlocution or without or
without any detour. Actual circumnavigation. Anyway, so בהדיא behedya directly.
Okay, so even that is not a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim, אמר,
Amar, so here is a whole discussion exactly about this issue of
usage, that even things closely connected to the street, if they're not
used as fully as the street or as easily for travel, it
is not a
רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. Okay. אמר רב זירא אמר רב יהודה, Amar
Rav Zeira Amar Rav Yehuda, so Rav Zeira in the name of
Rav Yehuda. אצטבא שלפני העמודים, itztava she'lifnei ha'amudim, the booths that are
before the pillars, נידון ככרמלית, nidon k'karmelis, is also like a כרמלית,
karmelis where the people go to look at the booth with the
wares, which is funny because according to Rashi, that was what was
meant by
the word אצטוונית itztovanis in the ברייתא, braisa, but okay. So he
wants to say like this: למאן דאמר, l'man d'amar, if you say
בין העמודים, bein ha'amudim, between the pillars is a כרמלית, karmelis כל
שכן אצטבא, kol shekein itztava, all the more so the booth area,
because the booth area is not where people move, like people move
between the pillars. The booth area is where you go and you
stand and you look at the wares, so certainly that's a כרמלית.
karmelis אבל למאן דאמר אצטבא, aval l'man d'amar itztava,
but if you only say the booth area is where it's a
כרמלית, karmelis. אצטבא הוא דלא ניחא תשמישתיה, itztava hu d'lo nicha tashmishtei,
that's because it's not a convenient place, you know, it's convenient to
stand there for a few minutes to look at the wares, but
it's not a convenient place to travel and to move and to
do other types of things. אבל בין העמודים, aval bein ha'amudim, but
if it would be between the pillars where you do sort of
move, דניחא תשמישתיה, d'nicha tashmishtei, which is more convenient use, more easy
to use that space, לא, lo, then that would not be a
כרמלית, karmelis that would actually be a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. Now
one of the things that needs to be asked as well, which
I'm sort of fudging here, which the גמרא Gemara will distinguish later,
is what type of use. Is it travel use or is it
use for other purposes as well? Partly the reason that's a little
unclear is because we normally immediately think of רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabbim
as a road, but there is one category of רשות הרבים reshut
ha-rabbim. which is a public square. So if people gather, it's also
considered a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim But here we are talking about,
so maybe if you're dealing with a square you're interested for use
in terms of, you know, a place to gather to do things.
But here at least it seems that the primary concern is a
place of traveling. So for example, the גמרא Gemara, before said אף
על גב דדרסי בה רבים, af al gav d'darsi bei rabbim, even
though the masses walk there, trample there, move there. So it seems
like primary use we're thinking about is how easy is it as
a means of, of you know, of travel, but that's not limited
to that and the גמרא Gemara will explicitly talk in a few
minutes also about other types of usage that way you can use
the רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim, So it's a little vague what we
mean by use. But either way, this place between the pillars is
a, is great as a place of easier use, easier travel than
when you step out and you're standing right there amongst the, among
the booths. Okay, so then we might make a distinction that way.
לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way of saying this, which was a
version of this statement, was that it was explicit already in the
statement, that
בין העמודים, bein ha'amudim, that he explicitly said by the booths it's
a כרמלית. karmelis. אבל בין העמודים, aval bein ha'amudim, between the
pillars, דזימנין דדרסי לה רבים, d'zimnin d'darsi lah rabbim, there are times
that the masses actually walk there, כרשות הרבים דמי, k'rishus harabbim dami,
that's like רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. Bit of difference between these two
versions, or
actually I take that back, it's not that רב זירא Rav Zeira
said that, but anyway, the גמרא, Gemara. different way of the גמרא
Gemara saying the distinction. But the difference between these two versions might
be exactly what I said, that the first version emphasizes it's a
more easy place for use in the generic and abstract, whereas the
second one said no, no, the booths is where you stand, between
the pillars is where you walk. Okay, so that also gets to
this question about is there greater significance attributed to a space of
travel for the use of רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabbim than other types
of use. Okay, is it just degree of ease or is it
use versus travel? Okay, and that will come up a little bit
later. אמר רבא בר שילא אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rava bar Shila
Amar Rav Chisda. לבינה זקופה, Levaina zekufa, now it was so fun,
we were all of a sudden talking about how to define domains,
now we're going to go back to the act of carrying. Okay,
לבינה זקופה, levaina zekufa, if you have a brick that has been
like
put erect, stood up,
ברשות הרבים, birshus harabbim, it's in the public domain, וזרק וטח בפניה
חייב, ve'zarack ve'tach b'faneha chayav, על גבה פטור. al gabah patur. This
also gets us to a domain question. So here's your, here's your
brick, it's in רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabbim. you throw something, some sticky
thing, the גמרא, Gemara yeah, gum would be a good example, okay,
some sticky and the גמרא Gemara imagines it's like you know some
fruit thing that's sticky, whatever, so you know a wad of that
fruit, דבלה, deveila, and it sticks against it, then you're חייב. chayav.
Why? Because it's has a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabbim. below it, it's
stopped, it's נח, nach, that's the
criteria. So as long as it's within the air space of רשות
הרבים reshut ha-rabbim. which goes up to ten טפחים, tefachim, you're חייב.
chayav. However, if it's on top of it you're פטור. patur. Why
are you פטור? patur? Let's find out.
Okay. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, Abaye ve'Rava d'amrei tarvaihu, and this is
if it's higher than three, דלא דרסי לה רבים, d'lo darsi lah
rabbim, that the masses do not walk on it. If it's within
three, it's a short brick and it's within three טפחים, tefachim about
nine inches or ten inches. from the ground, then it's considered to
be connected to the ground. Now how it's considered to be connected
to the ground can be two ways. People are probably aware that
there's a general rabbinic principle called לבוד, lavud, which means that anything
within three is considered connected. Now that is not—you'll notice Abaye and
Rava did not say that if it's within three you're חייב chayav
because of לבוד דמיא. lavud damya. Right, they didn't say לבוד. lavud.
They said because people walk on it. Why? Because by רשות הרבים,
reshut ha-rabbim, as we've said, it's not sufficient that it's structurally part
of רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim, It has to also be used as
a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. So if you had a low brick
that everybody walked around to avoid, even if structurally it was considered
to be on the ground, that space would be a non-רשות הרבים
reshut ha-rabbim, because the רבים rabim all move around it and they
avoid it. So it's only because people will walk over it and
they'll stomp on it, right, that therefore it also is considered in
terms of use part of the רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. So within
three it's part of the רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabbim because it gets
walked on and used and so on, fine. Why above three is
it not? Well, because then nobody is walking on it. If it
stood up, people are walking around it. So if it hits the
side, then you don't have to consider the brick the רשות הרבים,
reshut ha-rabbim. the space underneath it is the רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim.
Okay, but if it's on the top, then you have to consider
this space a רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabbim. and it is not, because
people don't walk, walk through it, they walk around it, so the
space on top is not רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim What is it?
If it's four by four טפחים, tefachim, which would be a pretty
big brick,
then it would be a כרמלית. karmelis, Four by four טפחים tefachim
without walls is a כרמלית carmelis? if it's not רשות הרבים. reshut
ha-rabbim. Okay, if it's less than four by four, it's a מקום
פטור. makom patur. Your classic מקום פטור makom patur is a structure
less than four by four טפחים, tefachim more than three טפחים tefachim
off the ground because within three טפחים tefachim. of the ground it
gets considered part of רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim More than three טפחים
tefachim off the ground and less than four by four טפחים. tefachim
Also not ten טפחים tefachim high, then it becomes a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. Somewhere between three and ten
טפחים tefachim in רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabbim, that's where fundamentally you will
find
your—it could be either a כרמלית carmelis or מקום פטור. makom patur.
Meaning most כרמליות karmeliyot are places that are not major streets and
not homes. But even within רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabbim. you can find
both a כרמלית carmelis, and a מקום פטור. makom patur. Where? So
within three טפחים tefachim, towards the ground, that becomes part of רשות
הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim, Higher than ten טפחים tefachim will often become a
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. if it's wide enough and big enough. But
between three and ten טפחים, tefachim about nine inches to about three
feet, that's where if it's four by four, if it's a real
space, it's a כרמלית carmelis. and if it's less than that, it's
a מקום פטור. makom patur. Okay, so that's going to be where
you're going to find your classic מקום פטור. makom patur. So in
this case on top, it's not a רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabbim it's
מקום פטור makom patur or כרמלית. carmelis. If it's here, then it
is considered on the ground, it faces the ground and it is
a רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabbim. That is because people are walking around
it.
Is it still considered רשות הרבים reshut harabim. though? No.
No, the side—no, it's only the ground underneath. Oh, you mean if
they have to—I was thinking about that, let's say they have to
avoid this, in terms they're not walking directly up against it. Yeah,
I think there we don't make that distinction, we don't look at
it with that much of a microscope. But if this is a
separate unit, we'll define this space as a non-רשות הרבים. reshut harabim
Okay, so one other point about this before we continue, which is
תוספות—there Tosafot are two opinions in תוספות Tosafot whether the face of
the brick has to be four by four. Remember we said something
has to rest on a space of four by four? So תוספות
Tosafot has two opinions. Is it that when it's here suspended in
mid-air it's like it's on the ground, and therefore it's considered on
a space four by four? Or is it only if the face
of the brick has four by four is it considered resting in
that type of space? But because it's opposite the ground, it's also
considered on the ground to be רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, So that
gets us back to our four by four discussion. Anyway, back to
the גמרא. Gemara The basic point in the גמרא Gemara is that
use again. So within three, not only is it structurally part of
the street, but people walk over it, and that makes it a
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim Now the גמרא Gemara is going to sort
of distinguish between cases, let's take a look.
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו והוא שגבוה שלושה, Abaye ve-Rava de-amri tarvayhu ve-hu
she-gavoha shelosha, when it's higher than three, that's when it's not a
רשות הרבים reshut harabim דלא דריסי ליה רבים, de-la darisi lei rabbim,
because people don't walk over on it once the brick is that
high. אבל היזמי והיגי, Aval hizmei ve-higi,
and lower than three, yes, it becomes part of רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim אבל היזמי והיגי, Aval hizmei ve-higi, if you have different types
of thorn bushes or thistles or types of things, אף על גב
דלא גביהי שלושה, af al gav de-la gevihai shelosha,
even if it's lower than three, that's not a רשות הרבים reshut
harabim. because people will avoid it. So very clear that it has
to be used as a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim it's not enough
that it's structurally part of רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, So you have
a thorn bush which is less than ג' טפחים, gimel tefachim, which
is very close to the ground, although structurally part of רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim. it is not רשות הרבים reshus harabim, because everybody walks
around it to avoid. וכי אתא רב אמר אפילו היזמי והיגי, Ve-ki
ata Rav amar afilu hizmei ve-higi,
even thorn bushes people will walk through and is a רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim אבל צואה לא, Aval tzoah lo, not excrement. Okay, dog
poop was a problem even then, much bigger problem then than that.
That people horse, horse poop, people will walk around, that, even though
interestingly you could say, you know, that's... kind of permanent part of
the structure, hopefully eventually that'll be cleaned up or washed away, so
maybe we should consider that the ground underneath is רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. No. Fascinating idea for the period that it is here, it
makes that space non-רשות הרבים reshus harabim, space because right now it's
not being used as such, which is very interesting, it speaks to
the fact that you go by current immediate usage. רב אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi amar, אשי Ashi says even צואה, tzoa, even excrement, people
would still walk through excrement if they needed to and whatever, you
know. So, I know. So or maybe he's saying, I maybe he's
saying I don't care if they walk through it, in the end
it'll get, you know, it's not a permanent part of רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim, it's not clear what his point is. But here what
you get clearly is, except for the last position which might disregard
it, that use matters even if it's structurally part of it and
perhaps even temporary use defines, even if it's not a permanent part
of the structure. Okay, now the question to ask in the flip
is let's say you have a space higher than three that is
used by the רבים. rabim, Do you need both criteria? Within three
it's structurally part, it's לבוד, lavud, and we say in addition to
being structurally part it has to be used by the רבים, rabim,
right? So there has to be walking through it and so on.
Let's say it's higher than three but it is used by the
רבים, rabbim. right? Would that also be רשות הרבים reshus harabim, or
does it have to be within the three of the ground? Is
that question clear? Right, you need both the structural or is usage
enough? So not to ruin the surprise, but I will tell you
that the גמרא Gemara tomorrow is going to say that if you
have like a little platform that's nine טפחים tefachim high, about like
shoulder height, which is conveniently used for like putting packages on and
arranging packages and taking it off. Like maybe a somewhat similar example.
Well, yeah. Well, no, those were those pillars used for but like
maybe I was thinking more like you have a, in the bathrooms,
the baby changing stations. So imagine you had something like that, some
nice convenient baby changing stations in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim, which are
made or very usable for the רבים but not for walking, and
they're not part of the ground. The גמרא Gemara is still going
to say it's because it's considered רשות הרבים reshut harabbim, if you
put something on it. So very interestingly it does not have to
be connected to the ground, it does not have to be space
that you walk on, as long as it's part of this domain
and it within the ten טפחים tefachim it does have to be,
but as long as it's within the ten טפחים tefachim and it
is used by the רבים, that is makes it a רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim So usage is much more critical here than the structural
concerns. Being within three טפחים tefachim. is not sufficient and higher than
three טפחים tefachim is not even necessarily a problem, it can be
part of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim. primarily based on the question of
usage. Okay, so that's what we really is the recurring theme here.
Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רבה דבי רב שילא. Amar
Rabbah d'bei Rav Shila. So רבה Rabbah said in from the house
of רב שילא, Rav Shila, כי אתא רב דימי, Rav Dimi when
רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan again another statement in the name of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan: אין כרמלית פחותה מארבעה. ein karmelis pchusah m'arba'ah. A כרמלית
carmelis. is not smaller than four by four טפחים. tefachim. Very critical
point, which is mostly as I said, כרמלית carmelis. you don't need,
it's not that tiny, a כרמלית carmelis. is a yard, it's any
place that's not a major thoroughfare and that's not a house. But
within the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim if you have these types of
things, these little pillars, these stands, these bricks, these small walls, so
what are they? If they're not ten טפחים tefachim, high, they're not
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, And if they're not walked on by
the רבים, they're not a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim, So our remaining
two choices are כרמלית carmelis? or מקום פטור. makom p'tor. So here
we are getting to the dividing line. To be a מקום פטור
makom p'tor it'd have to be less than four by four טפחים.
tefachim. Okay, it could be longer than four in one direction, but
if it's not four by four both length and width, it is
not a כרמלית. carmelis. A minimum size of a space to be
significant, like we say you're only חייב chayav if you put down
in a space four by four טפחים, tefachim. a minimum size of
a space to be significant is four by four, about a foot
by a foot. Anything less than that is a מקום פטור. makom
p'tor. And that's what רבי Rebbi? יוחנן said, if it's smaller than
that in wherever you'll find it, it's a מקום פטור, makom p'tor,
which is why we said like, you know, some types of things
you find yourself carrying stuff in the street, you look for some
type of thing like maybe a mailbox or although a mailbox might
be more than a foot by a foot, but like a hydrant,
fire hydrant, something that is less than a foot by a foot
is a מקום פטור. makom p'tor. אין כרמלית פחותה מארבעה. ein karmelis
pchusah m'arba'ah. כרמלית carmelis it cannot be smaller than four by four
טפחים. tefachim? ואמר רב ששת ve'amar Rav Sheshet and then רב ששת
Rav Sheshet came to qualify it, ותופסת עד עשרה, vetofeset ad asarah,
it grabs up until ten טפחים. tefachim מאי ותופסת עד עשרה? mai
vetofeset ad asarah? What does it mean it grabs up
until ten טפחים? tefachim אילימא דאיכא מחיצה עשרה הוא דהויא כרמלית ואי
לא לא הויא כרמלית, ileima d'ika mechitza asarah hu d'havia karmelis v'i
lo lo havia karmelis, if you say it needs to have a
wall of ten טפחים tefachim to be a כרמלית. carmelis Now everybody
should be jumping on me. One minute, if it has a wall
of ten טפחים tefachim. then it's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid What
does that mean? So רש״י seems to read the גמרא Gemara that
way which is a hard read, I'm going to tell you the
way תוספות Tosafot reads it which doesn't mean it's a wall, it
doesn't mean it literally, but it fits better in the example and
it fits better as a possibility. Maybe it cannot be a רשות,
reshus, a כרמלית, carmelis, unless it has ten טפחים tefachim of air
space. Meaning what if you had something that was that had a
a low ceiling and it didn't go high, it didn't even go
up ten טפחים. tefachim Okay, you had I'm trying to imagine what
the scenario would be, but I don't know. Let's say you had
a little hole in a wall, okay, which was, you know, four
טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim. wide, but it was only like
five טפחים tefachim high. So maybe that's not a כרמלית? carmelis. Maybe
a כרמלית carmelis. to be a domain, but מקום פטור makom patur
are like little spaces that you find. But conceptually, public domain, private
domain, כרמלית, carmelis a domain, the same way it needs four by
four to be significant, might need a height of ten. So if
there's a low roof that's its height is less than ten, maybe
it's not a כרמלית. carmelis? That makes a lot of sense, but
let's see now what the גמרא Gemara says.
Here's an example: a newspaper box that has an air space underneath
it.
Oh, okay, yeah, you mean what, okay, assuming that the box but
even in the newspaper box is a good example, that's four by
four, that's the bottom level inside, but it doesn't have an it
stops under ten טפחים. tefachim. So maybe it would have to be
like the domain, right, if you think about the classic domains, רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, certainly they're at least four
by
four, right, I mean רשות הרבים reshut harabbim has to be sixteen
אמות, amos but רשות היחיד reshus hayachid is four by four, and
they tend to be ten טפחים tefachim. high. So maybe if it's
not that, it can't be a כרמלית. carmelis. Okay, that's the possibility.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
והא אמר רב גידל אמר רב חייא בר יוסף אמר רב, Veha
amar Rav Gidal amar Rav Chiya bar Yosef amar Rav, but one
minute, that can't be, because we say in the name of
רב, Rav, בית שאין בתוכו עשרה וקירויו משלימו לעשרה. bayis she'ein besokho
asarah vekeruyav mashlimo le'asarah. You have a house that is very small,
it does not have, what?
Okay, well, yeah, anyway, but I would use that if it was
more four-dimensional, but anyway, here I'll use this.
Okay, so here's your house here, maybe I'll use this, it's good,
you can see
square by four.
Okay,
so here you go, here's your house. Okay, here's your house. Here
it is nine טפחים. tefachim. On the inside, it's only nine טפחים.
tefachim, Then you have a nice טפח tefach roof. Okay, so inside,
the air space is nine טפחים. tefachim. From the outside, you have
a wall of ten טפחים, tefachim. right? What's going to be the
status of this lovely house? So, let's see, oh, don't count that
as an actual physical example. Okay, fine, so what's the status? So
he says, so he says like
this, one minute, גגו מותר לטלטל בכולו. aggago mutar letaltel bekullo. If
you're on the roof, you're in a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid you
can carry on the roof, because the roof is a space that's
four by four and has walls of ten טפחים. tefachim, Even if
the walls are not creating an inner space, even if the walls
are like solid, you know, filled in the middle, they would imaginarily
be considered to extend above. And therefore, if you're on the roof,
you're between four walls that imaginarily extend above. So on the roof,
you're allowed to carry on the entire roof.
בתוכו, besokho, inside the house, let's call it the doghouse, אין מטלטלין
אלא ארבע אמות. ein metalpelin ela arba amos. You have to you
can only carry up to four אמות amos, like you can in
a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim You can't go more than four אמות,
amos, not because it's a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim. but because it's
a כרמלית. carmelis? So inside is a כרמלית. carmelis, It's four okay,
it's four by four, but it is not a רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid, because it doesn't have, from the inside perspective, it does not
have walls of ten טפחים. tefachim? So from the inside, you have
a space that's four by four, not a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
because it doesn't have walls that are ten טפחים, tefachim not a
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim. it's a כרמלית. carmelis. So what's the הלכה
halakha of a כרמלית? karmelit, You can only carry up to four
אמות, amot you can't carry more. So here on the top of
the house is a on the roof is a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid in the house is a כרמלית. karmelit. What do you see
though? You see that you have a כרמלית karmelit, that does not
have an air space of ten. So you can have a כרמלית
karmelit, that does not have an air space of ten. So in
terms of the area, less than four by four is not a
כרמלית, karmelit. it's a מקום פטור. makom patur. But in terms of
the height, the height can be less than ten and still be
a כרמלית. karmelit, So you see so that when you say you
need ten, it cannot mean that with less a height of ten
it's not, because even with something like this that doesn't have a
height of ten, it's still a כרמלית. karmelit, אלא מאי בתופסת עד
עשרה, ela mai bitofeses ad asarah, so what does it mean that
a כרמלית karmelit grabs up to ten טפחים? tefachim. A simpler point:
ועד י' הוא דהויא כרמלית. ve'ad yud hu dehavya carmelis. What about
the air space of a כרמלית? karmelit. Let's say we're talking about,
you know, a normal valley, right? Open air, no walls, but it's
not a domain, it's not a thoroughfare, it's a כרמלית. karmelit. How
high on the air space is still considered a כרמלית? karmelit So
just like a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim up until ten טפחים tefachim,
it's a כרמלית, karmelit למעלה מי' טפחים לא הוי כרמלית, lema'ala miyud
tefachim lo havei carmelis, higher than that is not a כרמלית. karmelit?
To remind ourselves what the rules are: a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid,
all
the way up to heaven is a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, with
the walls imagined to extend all the way up. Now, what does
that mean? I mean, to put an object in it, it has
to rest, right? So flying through the air space doesn't matter. But
an example would be, you know, and if it rests on top
of a platform, then maybe the platform is its own domain. So
a simple example would be simple, I don't know, but for simplicity's
sake, we're talking about, let's say you had Something that's sticking on
the side of a post, okay? So no matter how high it
is, it's not in a separate domain because it's on the side
of a wall, not on top of a wall. It's on the
side, so it's considered to be in the domain below. So רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid it goes up to the heaven. If it's רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, then it's standing, it's hitting up, it's on a
post, something stuck to a post within עשרה טפחים asara tefachim is
considered about three feet, is considered to be connect the airspace of
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim and you'd be חייב chayav if it hit
a post under עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and you had carried it
four אמות amot. or threw it four אמות. amot Higher than that
is considered מקום פטור. makom patur. Its airspace does not extend beyond
ten טפחים. tefachim, Similarly by a כרמלית, carmelis. rabbinically you can't carry
in a כרמלית. carmelis, If I were to carry in a כרמלית,
carmelis. throw something and it would stick on a post within the
first ten טפחים, tefachim, three feet, I would have transgressed rabbinically because
I carried in a כרמלית, carmelis. I put it down in a
כרמלית. carmelis. If it stuck on the post higher than עשרה טפחים,
asara tefachim, the airspace higher is a מקום פטור. makom patur. Okay,
so that is the relevance that the airspace does not extend.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
לא הוי כרמלית. lo havei karmelit. וכי הא דאמר ליה שמואל לרב
יהודה, vechi ha de'amar leh Shmuel leRav Yehuda, שיננא, shinena, sharp
one, לא תהוי במילי דשבתא למעלה מעשרה. lo tehei bemilei deShabbata lemala
me'asara. Don't be in the matters of שבת, meaning don't worry about
שבת issues above ten טפחים, tefachim. carrying issues above עשרה טפחים. asara
tefachim. למה הלכתא? lema hilchata? For what purpose? אילימא דאין רשות היחיד
למעלה מעשרה, elima de'ein reshut hayachid lemala me'asara, if you want to
suggest that a private domain is not considered to go higher than
עשרה
טפחים. asara tefachim. והאמר רב חסדא, veha'amar Rav Chisda, נעץ קנה ברשות
היחיד, na'atz kaneh bireshut hayachid, if you stuck a post in רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid וזרק ונח על גביו, vezarak venach al gabav, and
it went and it landed on the top of the post, אפילו
גבוה מאה אמה חייב, afilu gavoah me'ah amah chayav, even if it's
a hundred אמה amah high you're still חייב, chayav, מפני שרשות היחיד
עולה עד לרקיע, mipnei she'reshut hayachid olah ad larakia, because רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid. goes like all the way up to the sky. What?
Yeah, it is like that. Okay, so רשות היחיד reshut hayachid goes
all the way up. Now there's a question about like why isn't
it considered like, well, okay fine, there is a separate question which
we'll get to later, which is why don't you need a space
of ד' על ד'? arba al arba? We spoke about resting on
a space ד' על ד'. arba al arba. But we're going to
ignore that now. You have a super high post like a, what's
it called, like a flagpole and something lands on top of a
flagpole. It's in the, it's landed in the רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid goes all the way up. Okay, if it's
a flagpole in the middle of a house or whatever, a flagpole
surrounded by a fence and you throw something, even if it lands
on top of the flagpole, it's landed in the רשות היחיד. reshut
hayachid, Okay, so רשות היחיד reshut hayachid... goes all the way up.
כרמלית, carmelis. right. אלא, ela, so what does he, what did שמואל
Shmuel mean when he said things don't go higher than עשרה? asara?
He meant
דאין רשות הרבים למעלה מעשרה. de'ein reshut harabbim lemala me'asara. Maybe he
meant that, okay, a public domain airspace does not go higher than
ten. That is the הלכה. halacha. But that can't be what שמואל
Shmuel needed to tell רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. מתניתין היא. matnitin hi.
It's a משנה. Mishna תנן, tnan, we taught in the משנה Mishna.
later on, הזורק ד' אמות בכותל, hazorek arba amot bekotel, so, למעלה
מעשרה טפחים כזורק באויר, lemala me'asara tefachim kezorek ba'avir, למטה מעשרה טפחים
כזורק בארץ. lemata me'asara tefachim kezorek ba'aretz. This is the example I
gave you of throwing some type of a sticky thing that sticks
to the wall. If you throw something four אמות amot in a
רשות הרבים reshus harabim. and it hits a wall, hits the side
of a wall, if it's within עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, three feet
of the ground, it's like it's in the airspace on the ground.
You're חייב, chayav, you've carried it four אמות ammos. in רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim, If it lands on top of the wall, that, I'm
sorry, not on top, did I say
on top? Not on top, on top of the wall is a
separate issue. Above עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, then you are in non-רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim airspace. You're in open airspace, international waters. You are,
right, it is nobody owns that space and therefore you are okay.
So the basic הלכה halacha is that a private domain because of
the idea of walls, the walls are seen to extend up, all
the airspace above is related. And if it stops somewhere in midair
by being on a flagpole or the side of a wall, it's
like you put it down in that domain. Whereas in a public
domain, רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim. it's only the first ten טפחים, tefachim
only the first three feet. Okay, but if that's what שמואל Shmuel
was saying, that's a משנה. You wouldn't have to say that to
רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אלא אכרמלית. ela akarmelit. So what he's saying
is he must be coming to include the
כרמלית, carmelis. דאין כרמלית למעלה מעשרה. de'ein karmelit lemala me'asara. A כרמלית
carmelis, does not extend higher than ten. So now we have the
basic, גמרא Gemara is going to sum it up, but let me
just first say, the basic rules of what makes a כרמלית. carmelis,
A, it's a territory that is neither surrounded by walls, neither רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid nor a major thoroughfare, not רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim?
so it's pretty much everything, you know? Everything that isn't a house
and a major street is a כרמלית. carmelis Even in a רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim, you can get a כרמלית carmelis, if it is
like higher than ג' טפחים gimel tefachim like we discussed. It's not
something that is trampled on and used by the רבים. So you
can have little places in a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. like, you
know, post boxes and other types of little platforms that are a
כרמלית carmelis there as well. But what does it need to be
a כרמלית? karmelis, It needs to be four by four טפחים. tefachim
Less than that is a מקום פטור. makom patur. And the same
way רשות היחיד... reshus hayachid רשות היחיד reshus hayachid less than four
by four טפחים tefachim is not a space. What we did find
out is it doesn't have to be ten טפחים tefachim. high. Even
the inside of a doghouse, in the inside of one of those,
what are they, flyer boxes or whatever, even if it's not ten
טפחים tefachim high, that's still enough of a space to be a
כרמלית. karmelis? Okay,
that's true. But when you do have a כרמלית, karmelis the airspace
does not go higher than ten טפחים. tefachim So those are some
of the הלכות halachos of the כרמלית. karmelis, Now the גמרא Gemara
summarizes it. So it says like this: ואקילו בה רבנן מקולי רשות
היחיד ומקולי רשות הרבים. ve-akilu ba-rabbanan mikulei reshus hayachid u-mikulei reshus harabim.
On the one hand, we're strict on it, treating it like both
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. and רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. You can't carry
in it like you can't carry in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim,
You can't transfer from it to a different רשות, reshus. so in
that way it's both רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim because you can't carry to either other רשות. reshus, So one
way we're strict. But on the other way, in terms of what
are its parameters, we are willing to give it some of the
leniencies of each of those categories. מקולי רשות היחיד, mikulei reshus hayachid,
we give it the leniencies of רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. דאיכא מקום
ארבעה הוא דהויא כרמלית, de-ika makom arba ahu de-havya carmelis,
only if it's four by four like רשות היחיד reshus hayachid do
we consider it a כרמלית. Karmelis. ואי לא, ve-ilo, and if not,
מקום פטור בעלמא הוא. makom patur be-alma hu. It's this exempt space.
So anything, this is the basic rule for מקום פטור, makom patur,
anything that is a surface smaller than four by four, a foot
by a foot, is a מקום פטור. makom patur. And it's not
in a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. In רשות היחיד reshus hayachid it's
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid But anything that is smaller than four by
four, right, is a מקום פטור makom patur
if it's outdoors.
Right. And it's higher than three from the ground. Correct, thank you.
So number one, that's one leniency. Less than four by four is
not a כרמלית. Karmelis
And מקולי רשות הרבים, mikulei reshus harabim, we also gave the leniencies
of
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim. דעשרה טפחים הוא דהויא כרמלית, de-asarah tefachim hu
de-havya carmelis, only the airspace off of the ground up until ten
טפחים tefachim, is a
כרמלית. למעלה מעשרה טפחים לא הויא כרמלית. lemala me-asarah tefachim lo havya
carmelis. Higher than ten טפחים tefachim. is not a כרמלית. Again, off
the airspace would be a מקום פטור. makom patur. Okay, so it
needs four by four, it does not need a height of ten,
that it does not need, the inside of the small doghouse example.
But when you do have a כרמלית, its airspace only goes up
until ten טפחים, tefachim. does not exceed ten טפחים. tefachim. Yes, Mike?
Is there a reason why we wouldn't call it international waters? It
doesn't necessarily mean that I can really go in and like, you
know, use it, right?
But it does. Anything that is none of the first three is—really?
So let's say, you know, this like my house here, let's say
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim is right here. Right. I decide, you know
what, oh מקום פטור, makom patur, I'm just going to put like
a whole new ledge.
Yeah, but as soon as the ledge starts extending out, it becomes
a כרמלית, or it might even become a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
if it's got edges and barriers that are considered to go down.
Do I have to extend our רשות היחיד reshus hayachid out into
there?
Yeah. Yeah. But yes. Yes. Okay. But it might be a כרמלית
and then you've got a problem. But if it's a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid then you've extended it fine. You have רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid. suspended above רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim Okay, גופא. gufa. Let's take
a look. Actually it might actually make the space below it a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, because of the imaginary walls go down and
then the space below could be a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid Whatever,
we'll talk about it later. Okay, we'll see some of those cases
about the ledges later. Okay, now we're going to go back to
our little doghouse example. Okay, so we can use this as continued
as our visual example. גופא, gufa, let's go back and look at
the thing we quoted before. אמר רב גידל, amar Rav Giddel, remember
the difference between גופא gufa and אמר מר? amar mar? This is
something we quoted in passing as part of a discussion, now we're
going to look at it on its own terms.
אמר רב גידל אמר רב חייא בר יוסף אמר רב: amar Rav
Giddel amar Rav Chiya bar Yosef amar Rav: בית שאין תוכו י'.
bayis she-ein tocho yud. You've got your house, your doghouse here, inside
does not go, goes only up until nine טפחים. tefachim Okay, I
think this book here is making—oh no, it's this thing, okay. Anyway,
it's not helping, it's not stable. Anyway, fine. Inside it only goes
up until nine טפחים. tefachim.
וקירויו משלימו לעשרה. ve-kiruyo mashlimo le-asarah. It's got a thick roof of
a טפח, tefach, and that means from the outside it's ten טפחים
tefachim high even though from the inside it's only nine טפחים. tefachim
על גגו מותר לטלטל בכולו. al gago mutar letaltel bekulo. You can
carry on the entire roof because the roof is considered surrounded by
walls because the outer walls are ten טפחים tefachim high.
בתוכו, betoko, inside of it, אין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע אמות. ein
metaltelin bo ela be-arba ammos. The inside does not have walls ten
טפחים tefachim high. The inside only has walls nine טפחים tefachim. high.
That's the walls that face the inside. And therefore it's a כרמלית,
certainly not a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. certainly not a רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim. it's a כרמלית and you can only carry four אמות.
אמר אביי: amar Abaye: ואם חקק בו ארבעה על ארבעה והשלימו לעשרה
מותר
לטלטל בכולו. ve-im chakak bo arba al arba vehishlimo le-asarah mutar letaltel
bekulo. Let's say, however, you made, dog... Oh my God, I really
need to start bringing markers here. We've actually got a picture here.
Okay, I'm not sure everybody can see. Anyway, it's easy enough to
demonstrate. Okay, fine. It's easy enough to demonstrate. Okay, look, look, it's
easy enough to demonstrate. Here is, here is, here
is
your floor. The height here is only nine טפחים tefachim. until you
hit your roof. What you did though is you went ahead and
you dug a hole in the middle of your house, four by
four טפחים. tefachim. Anything less would not be significant. It has to
be a רשות, רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. needs four by four טפחים.
tefachim, From the floor of this hole to the roof is ten
טפחים. tefachim, So this hole is... It's a space four by four
טפחים, tefachim it has a height of ten טפחים, tefachim and it
is surrounded by walls. Now the walls are not, are not juxtaposed,
are not, right to it, are not right, are not right up
against it, they're way over here, but nevertheless it's a space surrounded
by walls. So that's what, like an, oh that's a good example,
right, like an atrium, exactly. So this space, this space is, has
the height, has the walls, although not the walls that are that
are connected to it, that space is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid
It says,
correct, correct, and I'll go back and discuss that in a minute.
Okay, מותר לטלטל בכולן. mutar letaltel bekulon. Now not only can you
carry in this space, you can even carry in these spaces. How
do these spaces change? These spaces are still not ten טפחים tefachim,
high. מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? הוו חורי רשות היחיד.
havei chorei reshus hayachid. They're like holes of a רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid? חורי רשות היחיד כרשות היחיד דמי, chorei reshus hayachid k'reshus hayachid
dami,
they are like the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. itself. What's a hole
of a רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid. They would use to store objects
in the holes in their wall. They had stone walls and had
niches like כגבתא, ke-geveta, and you would store objects in it. Now
that little hole in the wall, if you think about it, itself
is not a space that's four by four, ten טפחים tefachim high,
surrounded by walls, right? That little, you know, the main space is.
That little hole isn't. But nevertheless, because it serves the main space,
it's considered connected to it and it becomes also part of the
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Now it probably helps the fact, well, okay,
certainly it's not four by four טפחים, tefachim, etc. Now Michael is
right, it's helped by the fact that it's still within the, you
know, within the outer edges of the wall. If you had some
example where it actually was a hole, something you used that was
outside of your walls, presumably not. It is within the outer, but
it in its own terms is not a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
But it's within the walls and it serves the רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid. That makes it a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, So here too,
this is the רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. All these other spaces are
attached to it and, you know, sort of connected to it. Now
it might even be that this is a more trivial space than,
this is your living room and this is your bed, you know,
this is not the main space. But nevertheless, conceptually, we'll say it's
that at least if you have one space of רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid these are between the walls and they're connected and are part
of the same use, it's all considered an extension of the רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid Yes, Bobby?
I have a question. What if you have a structure that's thick
stone walls, and on two sides of this stone, very tall, very
old building, there are openings that are like four by four openings,
but don't go through the entire stone, so that would, right.
Here, if it goes through the entire stone, it's interesting because then
if it's used by the people in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim, on
their end, and the people in רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. on their
end, then which is it considered? And it might be halfway in
is רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and halfway out is רשות הרבים. reshus
harabbim. But we're talking about a scenario, it's actually in a way
easier if it doesn't go all the way through, then clearly it's
only connected to the interior of the house and not the exterior.
But what if it's only open to the exterior?
Opening it to the exterior only, then it clearly is not part
of the רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, If you have it used by
both, then it could be divided half and half and we're going
to get to something like that. Now I do want to say
a word about the walls not connected to the inner space. תוספות
Tosafot asks, we know by סוכה Sukkah this isn't good. If you
had סוכה, Sukkah, right, if you had סוכה, Sukkah, if you had
סכך schach here and the walls here, it's not good. Why is
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid different than סוכה? Sukkah? סוכה Sukkah the
walls have to be connected to the sort of סכך schach and
the usable space. So he gives one answer is is that well,
סוכה Sukkah has an additional requirement of סכך. schach. No, סכך. schach.
So it could be that in terms of the space, the space
has walls, but by סוכה Sukkah you also have the סכך schach
and there's a הלכה halacha that by the סכך schach has to
be connected to a wall and if you had סכך schach in
the middle and the walls out there, then the סכך schach isn't
connected to the wall, so it's the סכך schach that creates this
extra criteria. There also could be another concept related that a סוכה
Sukkah might be more based on this concept of a habitation, a
בית דירה. beis dira. And therefore it has higher demands. The same
way it has a demand for a roof, סכך, schach, it also
has higher demands of what it means in terms of the walls.
In a way it's true, meaning a סוכה Sukkah is it is,
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid let me reframe this, is a space
surrounded by walls. A סוכה Sukkah is a place with walls. A
סוכה Sukkah is a house, a house has walls. רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid is not a house. רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, is an area
surrounded by walls. You don't need a roof. Besides you don't need
a roof. This area is surrounded by walls. Distant walls, but surrounded
by walls. But a סוכה Sukkah is not a space surrounded by
walls, a סוכה Sukkah is a place with walls. It's like, it's
a house, it's an it's an edifice. Okay, רשות היחיד reshus hayachid...
is a space, not an edifice. So there as an edifice, it
has the walls connected to it. As a space, as long as
it's surrounded by walls. That seems to be the difference. One final
difference is that maybe it maybe it solves itself. Once these become
חורי רשות היחיד chorei reshus hayachid and become part of the רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid then it is connected to the wall. Because once
these are part of the
רשות היחיד... reshus hayachid, But then the question is, well, why couldn't
you do the same by סוכה? sukkah? Maybe you can, and so
on. But that is an interesting part of this הלכה halacha is
not just the הלכה halacha of the holes, the חורי, churei, the
associated spaces, but that it doesn't have to be connected to the
walls.
Next question is I don't understand why this is נגרר nigrar after
this.
I understand, I get it, that's a וייס Weiss חידוש. chiddush. As
long as you have a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and we halachically
we say the other things are considered to be because their usage
might be more important, but their הלכה halacha status is less important.
הלכה halacha status, this is a כרמלית, this is רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid so halachically the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. is the primary. Okay,
now the גמרא continues: דאתמר, de-itmar, because it was taught. חורי רשות
היחיד כרשות היחיד דמי. churei reshus hayachid ke-reshus hayachid dami. That we
can agree on. Holes in a wall of רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
are like a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid חורי רשות הרבים, churei reshus
harabbim, what about holes in a רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim Now, what
does that mean holes? It means you have a wall alongside רשות
הרבים, reshus harabbim exactly like we said, Bob's wall there, that also
faces the street, and the holes in the wall are used by
the people on the street. So this is an example of something
used by the people on the street but not used for walking.
Remember, I gave you another example about like
a platform and so on. Here's a hole used by them but
not used for walking. What's the status? So אביי אמר כרשות הרבים
דמי, Abaye amar ke-reshus harabbim dami, it's like רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim,
You put something in the hole, you've put it in רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim ורבא אמר לאו כרשות הרבים דמו, ve-Rava amar lav ke-reshus
harabbim damu, it's not.
אמר ליה רבא לאביי, amaleh Rava le-Abaye, let's see what the debate
is about. לדידך דאמרת חורי רשות הרבים כרשות הרבים דמי, lididach d-amart
churei reshus harabbim ke-reshus harabbim dami, you want to say that it
has a status like a רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, מאי שנא מהא
דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, mai shna me-ha de-chi-ata Rav
Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, what about what we just said on the
עמוד א', that when רב דימי came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and said in the name of רבי Rebbi יוחנן: לא נצרכה אלא
לקרן זוית
הסמוכה לרשות הרבים, that that little corner that's nicked off of רשות
הרבים Reshus Harabbim. is a כרמלית? Because it's not used. Right? Remember
we had the case that you had your main street and you
had a little like niche where sometimes people squeezed into but it
wasn't part of the main thoroughfare and it made it a כרמלית
because
it wasn't the primary use. So if that's a כרמלית, ודהוי כחורי
רשות הרבים, ve-de-havai ke-churei reshus harabbim, according to you, that niche should
be no worse than a little hole in a wall. It's something
that sometimes people use. So if sometimes they put objects in the
holes in the wall, sometimes people walk into that space, although it's
a little off the beaten track, let that be a רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabbim, So what's אביי's Abaye difference? התם לא ניחא תשמישתיה הכא
ניחא תשמישתיה. hasam lo nicha tashmishtei hacha nicha tashmishtei. That is not
so convenient to use; these holes in the wall are convenient to
use. And then it becomes a very qualitative assessment, or you could
even say quantitative, but anyway, it's a sliding scale. It's not an
easy thing to say yes or no, right? At the very, it's
a whole continuum. How
easy every judge every single phenomenon separately about how convenient is its
use. But that as I said, this discussion of use is primary
in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim, because it doesn't have the same structural
criteria as רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, does. So the primary question is:
how is it used? And therefore, things even that are physically connected
within three טפחים tefachim, to the ground, a little hole in the
wall, a little קרן זוית, keren zavis, a little corner, a little
niche, all those, one of the primary questions is going to be:
is it used by the רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim, and how easily
is it used? And only if it's sort of very easily used
and very commonly used, can we begin to consider it a part
of רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim, So that is the so רבא Rava
is more prepared to
say have a very high criteria to be רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
so the same way the קרן זוית keren zavis is not, the
holes are not. And אביי Abaye has a slightly lower criteria and
he's willing to consider more things to be a regular part of
the use of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim Yes.
I don't see why the hole in the wall, if it's larger
than four by four טפחים, tefachim would not be רשות היחיד Reshus
Hayachid. because it's a hole.
It might be, but let's say, let's say it's under ten טפחים,
tefachim. okay? So at which anyway it has to be under ten
טפחים tefachim, to be because רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. doesn't go higher
than ten טפחים. tefachim. So that's a good question. But if it's
higher than רשות הרבים reshus harabbim, ten טפחים, tefachim it might very
well be רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid but we're talking under ten טפחים.
tefachim, Okay, so now we have this whole idea that it's a
continuum and it's not all or nothing, and therefore every case, at
least according to אביי, Abaye, has to be assessed separately. So now
the גמרא says like this: תנן. tnan. So now we're going to
see whether we're which way we can prove this based on the
other evidence. הזורק ארבע אמות בכותל למעלה מעשרה כזורק באויר למטה מעשרה
כזורק בארץ. hazorek arba amos bekosel למעלה מעשרה kezorek ba-avir למטה מעשרה
kezorek ba-aretz. Okay,
so if you threw something higher than ten טפחים tefachim and it
hit a wall, it's higher than the air space of רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, so it's throwing in the air, it's nothing, it's מקום
פטור. mekom patur. Under ten טפחים, tefachim it's within the air space
of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. and it's like you placed it down
on the ground and you're חייב. chayav. והוינן בה, ve-havina beh, מאי
כזורק בארץ? mai kezorek ba-aretz? What does it mean it's like you
threw it and it hit the ground? והא לא נח, veha lo
nach, it didn't stop! Okay, which meaning the גמרא assumes that maybe
I don't know, I mean, it says that you hit it against
the wall, maybe it assumes it bounced back, okay? Or maybe it
landed, or it could have also, like, if it landed on
the
wall...
This is your wall and it’s less than ten טפחים tefachim high,
it’s eight טפחים tefachim. high, then the top of the wall is
not רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, right? ‘Cause it’s not facing the ground
of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim People don’t walk over the wall, right?
As we said before you don’t walk over the thornbushes. If it’s
four by four it’s a כרמלית. If it’s less than four by
four it’s a מקום פטור. Makom Patur. So if it’s hit the
side of the wall, then it’s in top of the wall, it
bounced back. So what’s the scenario? Well that’s what I’ve been telling
you, but we haven’t said that yet, ואמר רבי יוחנן V’amar Rabbi
Yochanan so here’s what I’ve been telling you all along, בדבילה שמנה
שנו bidveilah shmeinah shanu
we talked about a fat
sticky דבילה dveilah which is like a round of I think dates
or figs, I keep getting confused, what does it say? Let me
look in the English. I keep on forgetting whether דבילה dveilah is
dates or figs. Anyway one of them, some type of sticky fruit,
okay, that it stuck to the side of the wall. That’s what
I’ve been- so that’s the case I’ve been describing it. Dates, figs,
okay fine. Okay, so it’s a figs that stick to the wall.
ואי סלקא דעתך V’ei salka dach so that’s our scenario. Fine, that’s
what we’ve been saying until now. ואי סלקא דעתך חורי רשות הרבים
כרשות הרבים דמו V’ei salka dach chorei Reshus Harabbim k’Reshus Harabbim damu
if you would say, says רבא Rava to אביי, Abaye,
that holes in a wall count as the רשות הרבים, למה לי
לוקמי בדבילה שמנה lamah li lokmi bidveilah shmeinah why do I have
to give such a bizarre case of sticky figs that are sticking
to the wall? A much easier case of how you can throw
something at a wall and it stays in the wall, it doesn’t
have to be sticky, it could land in a hole. So I
have a much easier scenario. לוקמי בצרור וחפץ Lokme bitsror v’cheifetz just
talk about a rock or any object, doesn’t have to be a
sticky thing, ודנח בחור v’danach b’chor
it landed in a hole. So again, can’t land on top of
the wall because that’s a כרמלית or מקום פטור. Makom Patur. It
has to be on the side. But why do you make this
crazy case of a sticky fig? Why not assume like it says
רבא Rava to אביי Abaye if the holes in the wall that
are used by pieces, by people, count as רשות הרבים, so just
say you threw something and it went into one of the holes
in the wall. A very easy scenario. Very good question. So let’s
see what he answered. זימנין משני ליה Zimnin meshani lei sometimes he
answered him, צרור וחפץ מיהדר ואתי. tsror v’cheifetz miahdar v’ati.
That’s also unrealistic. You try to throw a rock into a hole
in the wall, it’s going to bounce back. Okay, so it would
not be- he actually thought that the sticky fig was a more
reasonable scenario than exactly getting something to go into the hole and
stay in the hole. Okay, sticky fig. You could have combined, but
you didn’t have to. It’s sort of like those carnival games where
you try to throw something, it looks so easy, but to get
it to go and to stay there is really hard. Okay, so
that we didn’t want to give, that was a less reasonable scenario.
ואתי V’ati and it bounces back. זימנין משני ליה Zimnin meshani lei
sometimes he says בכותל דלית ביה חור. b’kosel d’leis bei chor.
We’re talking about a wall without holes. Now that’s not a really
good answer because so talk about a wall with holes. But now
he’s going to explain to you why we have to be assuming
it doesn’t have holes. ממאי Mimai how do I know that we’re
assuming it doesn’t have holes? דקתני רישא D’katani reisha because the first
case was זרק למעלה מעשרה טפחים כזורק באויר zaraka l’ma’ala mei’asarah tefachim
kezorek b’avir
when it’s higher than ten טפחים tefachim and is on the side
of the wall, then you’re in free zone. It’s like throwing in
the air, you’re exempt, it’s higher than ten טפחים. tefachim, כזורק באויר.
Kezorek b’avir. ואי סלקא דעתך V’ei salka dach and if you want
to say בכותל דאית ביה חור b’kosel d’is bei chor now if
you want to say that we should give an example that when
you threw under ten it went into a hole, so when we’re
talking about throwing higher than ten טפחים tefachim we would also want
to be talking about the parallel case. You threw into a hole.
But if you’ve got a hole in a wall higher than ten
טפחים, tefachim Charlie would tell us that it’s a what?
Well it depends on the size.
Okay, but if it’s four by four it would be a רשות
היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. So how could you say that
going in a hole, below I understand that would be רשות הרבים,
but above that might be a scenario of רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid.
and we want to get you into free zone. So therefore we’re
talking about sticking on the side of the wall because going into
a hole in the wall could be a case of going into
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. ואי סלקא דעתך בחור V’ei salka dach b’chor
if it has a hole, אמאי כזורק באויר amai kezorek b’avir why
when you throw in the hole in the wall higher than ten
טפחים tefachim is it like it’s in the middle of the air
and you’re exempt? הנח בחור Hanach b’chor
it’s in a hole and that should make it a רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid, Now, דתימא משום דלית ביה ארבעה על ארבעה d’teima mishum
d’leis bei arba al arba
ah,
maybe we’re talking about a hole that doesn’t have four by four.
So under ten it’s part of רשות הרבים, higher than ten it’s
a מקום פטור. Makom Patur. Maybe that could be the case. No,
that still won’t work. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב חייא V’amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav Chiya זרק למעלה מעשרה טפחים והלכה ונחה בחור כלשהו
zaraka l’ma’ala mei’asarah tefachim v’halcha v’nachah b’chor kol shehu
if you threw higher than ten טפחים tefachim and it went into
the hole of a wall, even if it was a small hole,
not four by four, באנו למחלוקת רבי מאיר ורבנן banu l’machlokes Rabbi
Meir v’Rabbanan
we came to a- this is the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and the Rabbis in עירובין, Eruvin, a debate about what? רבי
מאיר סבר חוקקין להשלים Rabbi Meir savar chokekin l’hashlim רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you carve out to give yourself the requisite size. ורבנן
סברי אין חוקקים להשלים, v'Rabbanan savri ein chokkim l'hashlim, you don't carve
out. Now what does that mean? Their debate is about a case
of an arch and whether it's חייב במזוזה. chayav b'mezuzah. You
have here a doorway that's got less than ten טפחים tefachim high.
Door has to be ten טפחים tefachim. high on the inside. Okay,
thank you. Ten טפחים tefachim, high on the inside to be חייב
במזוזה, chayav b'mezuzah, right? That actually is a good picture because that's
your classic arch. Anyway, your classic arch will be built up higher
and have a curved area like this. The problem is that even
when you get to the top of the curved area, it is,
maybe I need this too. Anyway, can you give me that pamphlet
over there? That, yeah, hand that to me. So you've got your
curved area like this, right? It's maybe not so good.
Give me, no, no, no,
do it like a little... No, it doesn't show... Oh, I see.
Good point. Okay, thank you. Thank you, thank you. Okay. Okay, yes.
So you've got your curved area like this. When it gets to
the top of the curve, it's not ten טפחים. tefachim But if,
I mean it is, excuse me, it is ten טפחים, tefachim but
it's not four טפחים tefachim wide. The top of the curve is
very narrow. The only way you could get ten טפחים high by
four טפחים wide is if rather than coming to a point, you
would square it off. So you would go as high as the
top of the curve, but you wouldn't come in, you would square
it off. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that's good enough. We
envision it as if you could square it off. We cut away
imaginarily the stone, and it's like you have ten high by four
by four. The חכמים Chachamim say we don't cut it away. It's
sort of like they asked Michelangelo how he was able to make
the David statue. He says, I just cut away everything that wasn't
David.
So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir cuts away everything that isn't ten by
four, and he gets his space. So הגמרא haGemara says maybe the
same debate would be if you have a little hole in a
wall, that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says as long as you've got
the space that you could in theory cut out the wall to
make the requisite space, then we imagine as if it's already done
and that constitutes enough to be here for a
מזוזה, mezuzah, therefore רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid So therefore, what הגמרא haGemara
is saying is,
I could not have given a scenario of going in a hole
in a wall that would work for under ten for רשות הרבים,
but higher than ten, if it was four by four, it would
be רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid higher than ten, four by four, and
even less than four by four, at least רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
would have said it was a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and I
don't want to get into those debates. So that's why we gave
the example of a sticky fig and not a hole in a
wall, because a hole in a wall higher than ten would be
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, if it's four by four and even
less according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would still be a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid, because you would imagine it as if that space
was cut out.
Okay? So אלא לאו שמע מינה דכותל דלית ביה חור, ela lav
shma mina d'kosel d'leis bei chor, so therefore not to get into
any of that, we had to assume we're talking about a wall
without a hole. שמע מינה, shma mina, that is a good point.
So therefore, says אביי, Abaye, that's why we're talking about a sticky
fig, but you know what? If it did go into a hole,
a hole of a רשות הרבים would count as a רשות הרבים.
So now we are seeing that, again, notice by the way by
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. nobody raised the questions of is it ניחא
תשמישתיה nicha tashmishtei. or not ניחא תשמישתיה. How convenient is it to
use? By רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. the primary definition is structural. It's
between the walls, it's four by four, as long as it has
some use, somehow connected, it's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But by
רשות הרבים, one of the, if not the primary criteria is function
and use. And therefore רבא Rava says, as long as it's not
the main use, forget it. אביי Abaye says, it's not so black
and white. And that maybe a קרן זוית keren zavis is not
a רשות הרבים, but something that's convenient like a hole would be
a רשות הרבים. Let's just read, get to the very bottom.
גופא. Gufa. Let's go back to again to the thing we quoted
before. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, נעץ קנה ברשות היחיד. na'atz
kaneh b'reshus hayachid. Now we have the idea of the beanpole, of
the whatever, the flagpole in a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. וזרק ונח
על גביו, v'zarak v'nach al gabav,
and you threw something, you have a flagpole it's surrounded by a
little fence, that's רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, You threw something, yeah, but
you could imagine a flagpole surrounded by a fence, you know? So
you got a flagpole surrounded by a fence, you throw it, it
went on the top of the flagpole, so you threw it from
רשות הרבים, ונח על
גביו, v'nach al gabav, אפילו גבוה מאה אמה, afilu gavo'ah me'ah ama,
even a hundred אמה ama tall, even 100 feet, 200 feet, חייב.
chayav. Why? מפני שרשות היחיד עולה עד לרקיע. mipnei she'reshus hayachid ola
ad l'rakia.
Once you have those walls on the bottom, you imagine them as
extending all the way up, and therefore it rested in a רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. Now הגמרא haGemara revisits a question it's been asking
from a few days already. הגמרא haGemara says, לימא רב חסדא דאמר
כרבי. leima Rav Chisda d'amar k'Rebbi.
Maybe this is going like רבי Rebbi. because הגמרא's haGemara problem is
going to be it might be in רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid but
it's not on a space that's four by four. We've been saying
that an object has to rest on a space four by four.
Maybe this is going like רבי? Rebbi דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, זרק ונח על גבי זיז כל שהוא, zarak v'nach al
gabei ziz kol shehu, you threw something presumably in רשות הרבים and
it landed on a little protrusion presumably in רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid.
רבי מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rebbi mechayev v'Chachamim potrin. רבי says you're חייב
chayav and חכמים say you're exempt. And presumably, what's the debate? Now
it's not the debate how high רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid goes.
Okay so maybe that idea anything with a
roof is
like a house that's filled. Okay so maybe that idea extends to
an entire רשות היחיד. reshut ha-yachid. And that's what we're assuming of
רב חסדא's Rav Chisda statement. That to be on top of a
beam on top of a flagpole what he's saying is that at
least in a רשות היחיד he doesn't need it to be on
a space of four by four. Okay so maybe this is like
רבי. That's what רבי seems to say. A זיז כלשהו ziz kol-she-hu
a little protrusion you're חייב chayav even though it's not four by
four. So I and if you read the parentheses it spells it
out אלמא לא בעינן מקום ארבע על ארבע alma lo ba'inan makom
arba al arba you see you don't need four by four. So
let's just see what the גמרא's answer is. אמר אביי amar Abaye
בריש דף ק' עמוד א' be-reish daf kuf amud aleph ברשות היחיד
be-reshut ha-yachid oh it's already it's already 8:30.
So we will find out the answer tomorrow about what is the
story of whether you need a place of four by four in
a רשות היחיד.